A Guide to the Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial records, Counsel's Office, Series 10 FA358
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Robert R. Douglass, 1959-1972; 3; 65 Document Box(es)
  - Education - Long Island University, 1967-1968 (Box 8, Folder 91)
    Memo on proposed sale of the Brooklyn Center of Long Island University (LIU) to City University of New York (CUNY), correspondence with constituents opposed to the sale.
  - Education - New York State Historic Trust, 1966 (Box 8, Folder 92)
    Three items, includes draft legislation for establishment of New York State Historic Trust (NYSHT) and memo on strategy for selecting its chairman.
  - Education - New York University, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 93)
    Correspondence on proposed state purchase of New York University Bronx campus at University Heights; two letters on New York University financial crisis.
  - Education - Optometric Center, 1970-1971 (Box 8, Folder 94)
    Two items on proposed purchase of New York Optometric Center building in New York City for State University of New York College of Optometry.
  - Education - O'Neill Proposal (Pre-School), 1967 (Box 8, Folder 95)
    One item on proposal for state funding of pre-school programs.
  - Education - School Aid, 1966 (Box 8, Folder 96)
    Correspondence, statements, draft legislation on increasing ceiling for operating aid from $600 to $660 per pupil in weighted average daily attendance.
  - Education - Select Committee on Higher Education, 1967 (Box 8, Folder 97)
    Clippings; press release on creation of Committee; "Changing Patterns of Public and Private Support for Higher Education," by Greyson Kirk, President of Columbia University.
  - Education - State University of New York - General, 1969-1971 (Box 9, Folder 98)
    Correspondence and clippings on issues on SUNY and various campuses.
  - Education - State University of New York - 1970 Program, Legislative Proposal #1, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 99)
    Budget report and draft legislation to require approval of the Director of the Budget for appointments above minimum salary to positions in non-professional service.
  - Education - State University of New York - 1970 Program, Legislative Proposal #3, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 100)
    Budget report and draft legislation to sell a small piece of state land to Alfred University.
  - Education - State University of New York - 1970 Program, Legislative Proposal #5, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 101)
    Draft legislation to give members of the discontinued Employees and Teachers Retirement Systems the benefit of subsequent improvements in retirement benefits.
  - Education - State University of New York - 1970 Program, Legislative Proposal #6 (Box 9, Folder 102)
    Budget report, correspondence and draft legislation to permit SUNY employees to work until the end of the academic year after reaching mandatory retirement age.
  - Education - State University of New York - 1970 Program, Legislative Proposal #8 (Box 9, Folder 103)
    Correspondence and draft legislation to create new guidelines for submitting and coordinating master plans from state, city and privated universities.
  - Education - State University of New York - Capital Construction Program, 1967, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 104)
    Budget projections of State University Construction Fund.
  - Education - State University of New York - SUNY Cobleskill, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 105)
    Three items on criminal charges against various students and staff at SUNY Cobleskill resulting from an unspecified incident.
  - Education - State University of New York - Drugs, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 106)
    Report on Drug Abuse and Drug Education Programs submitted to Joint Legislative Committee on Crime.
  - Education - State University of New York - Faculty, 1960-1964 (Box 9, Folder 107)
    Clippings and correspondence on faculty salaries and the issue of attracting and retaining high quality professors.
  - Education - State University of New York - Full Opportunity, c. 1970 (Box 9, Folder 108)
    Draft legislation to increase state aid to community colleges which adopt plans of full opportunity.
  - Education - State University of New York - Master Plan, 1969-1970 (Box 9, Folder 109)
    Five pieces of miscellaneous correspondence on SUNY Master Plan.
  - Education - State University of New York - SUNY New Paltz, 1969-1970 (Box 9, Folder 110)
    Correspondence and clippings on student unrest and administrative problems at SUNY New Paltz.
  - Education - Textbook Bill, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 111)
    Three memos on legislation to increase state financial aid to local school districts for text books for grades 7 through 12.
  - Education - United Federation of Teachers, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 112)
    Four pieces of United Federation of Teachers promotional literature; two printed bills on United Federation of Teachers related legislation. No correspondence.
  - Education - Vassar College, 1967 (Box 9, Folder 113)
    Correspondence on possibility of Vassar College moving and merging with Yale University and possible state initiatives to get Vassar to stay or to replace it with another institution.
  - Environmental Conservation - General, 1970-1972 (Box 9, Folder 114)
    Two booklets on Entomology-Plant Pathology Laboratory at the New York State Agricultural Experimental Station, Geneva, New York, Cornell University, c. 1970; part of draft for "Our Environment Can be Saved," by NAR, 1970, with some edits; memo on opposition to new Board of Cooperative Educational Services (BOCES) garage in North Castle; memo on meeting of Susquehanna River Basin Commission; NAR remarks at Environmental Teach-In, Albany, April 21, 1972.
  - Environmental Conservation - Air Pollution, 1964 (Box 9, Folder 115)
    Five page memo with recommended air pollution program.
  - Environmental Conservation - Air Pollution Package, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 116)
    Correspondence, outlines and draft legislation for air pollution program providing for expanded powers of Air Pollution Control Board; includes budgetary implications.
  - Environmental Conservation - Beauty Program (Natural), 1966 (Box 9, Folder 117)
    Outlines, NAR remarks, and draft legislation for proposed Natural Beauty Commission.
  - Environmental Conservation - Environmental Bond Issue, 1971-1972 (Box 10, Folder 118)
    Correspondence, outlines, opinion polls, reports, fact sheets, etc. on the purpose, size, and presentation of the $1.15 billion Environmental Quality Bond Act of 1972.
  - Environmental Conservation - Statement on Environmental Needs, 1972 (Box 10, Folder 119)
    Department of Environmental Conservation Commissioner Harry L. Diamond's "Statement on Long Range Environmental Needs," February 24, 1972, 8 pages, and press reaction.
  - Environmental Conservation - Environmental Facilities Corporation, 1971-1972 (Box 10, Folder 120)
    Correspondence on review of Environmental Facilities Corporation and its future, plans for restructuring it and redefining its purpose. A fairly complete file with input from NAR.
  - Environmental Conservation - Great Lakes Commission, 1971-1972 (Box 10, Folder 121)
    Correspondence on formation and purpose of the commission.
  - Environmental Conservation - Gore Mountain Ski Center, 1971 (Box 10, Folder 122)
    Complaint about possible faulty construction of ski left towers at Gore Mountain Ski Center.
  - Environmental Conservation - Highway Beautification, 1966-1967 (Box 10, Folder 123)
    Correspondence and draft legislation for three bills to regulate billboards and junk yards along major highways; explanation of federal money which will become available with the passage of the bills; exchange of frank letters between Norman Simpson, president of the Outdoor Advertising Association of New York, and Sol Corwin, general counsel to the Department of Public Works.
  - Environmental Conservation - Land Development, 1972 (Box 10, Folder 124)
    Draft of bill to amend the Environmental Conservation Law regulating land development.
  - Environmental Conservation - Land Reclamation, 1971-1972 (Box 10, Folder 125)
    Draft legislation and budget department reports recommending disapproval of proposed law regulating strip mining and related land reclamation.
  - Environmental Conservation - Long Range Programs, Conservation Department, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 126)
    Typescript, bound reports of program plans and projections with charts, dated June 1966. Parks and Recreation, Lands and Forests, and Motor Boats.
  - Environmental Conservation - Long Range Programs, Conservation Department, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 127)
    Oil and Gas, Fish and Game, Water Resources.
  - Environmental Conservation - Muskie Bill, 1971-1972 (Box 11, Folder 128)
    Correspondence on desired amendments to the federal Water Pollution Control Act. The act mandated "no discharge" by 1985 but did not provide adequate funding to states to meet the mandate.
  - Environmental Conservation - Offshore Drilling, Oil, 1972 (Box 11, Folder 129)
    Memos, proposed statements, clippings on need for national policy on off-shore drilling.
  - Environmental Conservation - Tocks Island Reservoir, 1971 (Box 11, Folder 130)
    Four items on New York State reservations over project supported by the Delaware River Basin Commission.
  - Environmental Conservation - Recap Island, 1972 (Box 11, Folder 131)
    Correspondence, reports, and clippings on proposed man-made island in Lower New York Harbor made of refuse to act as a site for power plants, recycling and recreation. Plan put forth by Pope, Evans and Robins, consulting engineers.
  - Environmental Conservation - Youth Environmental Service Proposals, 1971 (Box 11, Folder 132)
    Establishment of a comprehensive program of employing youths in New York State environmental programs.
  - Environmental Conservation - Water Pollution, 1964, 1970 (Box 11, Folder 133)
    Four items, includes 13-page, 1964 memo on the legal implications and requirements of a state water pollution program.
  - Environmental Conservation - Water Pollution Control Enforcement Bill, 1964-1965 (Box 11, Folder 134)
    Correspondence, press releases, and clippings on state grants to study regional sewage and drainage needs, the 1964 drought and attendant water shortage. Correspondence and draft legislation for bills to improve the enforcement of water pollution laws.
  - Environmental Conservation - Water Pollution and Water Supply, 1968-1970 (Box 11, Folder 135)
    A miscellaneous file on water and air pollution issues and measures.
  - Clemency, 1965 (Box 11, Folder 136)
    Counsel's reports on applications for the Governor's annual Christmas clemency for convicted criminals. Each report includes the personal history of the individual, the facts of the crime, the reason for the appeal for clemency, and counsel's recommendation. The final decision is not noted here.
  - Clemency - Christmas Package, 1965 (Box 11, Folder 137)
    Reports on ten applications.
  - Clemency - Christmas Package, 1966 (Box 11, Folder 0137A)
  - Fiscal - Budget, 1959 (Box 12, Folder 138)
    Correspondence, statistics and press releases on 1959 budget.
  - Fiscal - Budget, 1960-1961 (Box 12, Folder 139)
    Proposed increases; suggestions; budget message (draft).
  - Fiscal - Budget, 1961-1962 (Box 12, Folder 140)
    Draft budget message; miscellaneous memos; budget summary; selected statistics; studies.
  - Fiscal - Budget, 1962-1963 (Box 12, Folder 141)
    Executive Budget Message (draft); Capital Construction proposals; summary of budget items; memos.
  - Fiscal - Budget, 1965-1966 (Box 12, Folder 142)
    Correspondence; checklist of studies; statistics.
  - Fiscal - Budget - 1965 Budget, (Democrat) Reductions (Box 12, Folder 143)
    Two copies of State Purposes Proposed Reductions, for Counsel to the Governor Sol Neil Corbin and Budget Director T. Norman Hurd; each has edits.
  - Fiscal - Budget - Supplemental Budget Bill Items, 1966 (Box 12, Folder 144)
    Copy of proposed legislation to enact a supplement budget in 1966.
  - Fiscal - Budget - Supplemental Budget Justifications, 1966 (Box 13, Folder 145)
    Copy of justifications for proposed supplemental budget items.
  - Fiscal - Budget, 1971-1972 (Box 13, Folder 146)
    Correspondence, statistical tables, and press releases on impending fiscal crisis; suggested reductions in 1971-72 executive budget; reviews of budget problems in other states; public statements and fact sheets from Mental Hygiene Commissioner Alan Miller and State Environmental Conservation Commissioner Henry Diamond on impact of budget cuts in their departments; NAR press release on cuts.
  - Fiscal - Annual Messages, 1959-1964 (Box 13, Folder 147)
    Copies of the Governor's annual message to the State Legislature outlining legislative initiatives for the upcoming session and their broad budgetary implications.
  - Fiscal - Cigarette Tax Problem (Bootlegging), 1971-1972 (Box 13, Folder 148)
    Correspondence and reports on cigarette tax revenue, cigarette smuggling, and the problem of enforcing state cigarette taxes; statements and correspondence with Morris Weintraub, Managing Director of the Wholesale Tobacco Distribution of New York, on enforcing existing tax laws rather than increasing state cigarette taxes.
  - Fiscal - Comptroller Audit Reports, 1964-1967 (Box 13, Folder 149)
    Report on an Examination of Fidelity Bond Coverage in the State of New York, 1964; audit report on Housing Finance Agency, 1965; memos on audits of 21 state agencies.
  - Fiscal - Fiscal Crisis, 1971-1972 (Box 14, Folder 150)
    Reports; memos on taxes.
  - Fiscal - Fiscal Crisis, 1971-1972 (Box 14, Folder 151)
    Tax Reform proposals.
  - Fiscal - Fiscal Crisis, 1971-1972 (Box 14, Folder 152)
    Projected Budget Gaps reports; memos on meeting with John Mitchell; explanations of crisis.
  - Fiscal - Fiscal Crisis, 1971-1972 (Box 14, Folder 153)
    Memos on increased taxes; new taxes, surcharges, news conferences by NAR 12/14/71; press releases; proposed legislation.
  - Fiscal - Fiscal Crisis, January-February 1972 (Box 14, Folder 154)
    Legislative press release; statement by Republicans; NAR press conference; summons and complaint in lawsuit by Arthur Levitt as Comptroller against NAR as Governor to declare lump sum budget bills unconstitutional.
  - Fiscal - Fiscal Crisis, March-May 1972 (Box 14, Folder 155)
    Press release by Arthur Levitt; press release by Assembly Speaker; summary of Democrats' concerns; Robert R. Douglass score card on budget bills; correspondence with City University of New York.
  - Fiscal - Federal Revenue Sharing, c. 1972 (Box 15, Folder 156)
    Robert R. Douglass notes; NAR handwritten note on Statement by the Republican Governors' Association on revenue sharing: "I don't think Washington fully realizes what's happening at the local level and the political consequences."
  - Fiscal - Federal Revenue Sharing, 1970-January 1971 (Box 15, Folder 157)
    Correspondence; memos; letter to President Nixon; notes for NAR testimony before Joint Economic Committee (JEC); press release by NAR on Nixon State of the Union address; NAR statement to JEC; National Governor's Conference release on revenue sharing; transcript of NAR testimony before JEC 1/29/71; Jerry Bruno memo to Robert R. Douglass on creation of Citizen's Committee on Revenue Sharing.
  - Fiscal - Federal Revenue Sharing, February-March 1971 (Box 15, Folder 158)
    Memos; correspondence on prospects in Congress on revenue sharing; Proclamation: "Revenue Sharing Day" February 22, 1971; reports on local "Revenue Sharing Day" programs; Sen. Buckley's proposal on revenue "shifting."
  - Fiscal - Federal Revenue Sharing, April 1971 (Box 15, Folder 159)
    National Conference of Governor's reports; strategy memos; correspondence; research memos.
  - Fiscal - Federal Revenue Sharing, May 1971-1972 (Box 15, Folder 160)
    Material for NAR for his testimony before U.S. House Ways & Means Committee (Wilbur Mills); material from tax administrators; summary of Mills' bill.
  - Fiscal - Long-Range Program Planning Book, 1965 (Box 15, Folder 161)
    Guidelines and Instructions for Preparation of Long-Range Program Planning Submissions, prepared by the Division of the Budget for use by state agencies.
  - Fiscal - Mills Bill, 1971-1972 (Box 15, Folder 0161A)
    Correspondence on U.S. Congressman and House Ways and Means Committee Chair Wilbur Mills' Intergovernmental Fiscal Coordination Act of 1971, and briefing material for meeting of New York State Congressional delegation with state, county, city, town, and school officials and state legislative leaders on the state fiscal crisis and the Mills Bill.
  - Fiscal - Municipal Bonds, 1969 (Box 15, Folder 162)
    Correspondence, clippings, statistical tables on cost of issuing municipal bonds, especially school district bonds; includes background data (1957-1963) on comptroller Arthur Levitt's School Bond Authority.
  - Fiscal - New York City Tax Proposals, 1966 (Box 16, Folder 163)
    Analysis of New York City Mayor John V. Lindsay's personal and business tax proposals.
  - Fiscal - New York City Tax Proposals, 1966 (Box 16, Folder 164)
    Final version of proposed city personal and business tax legislation; copy of Internal Revenue Code.
  - Fiscal - New York State Departments of Audit and Control, 1958-1961 (Box 16, Folder 165)
    Memoranda and press releases on running feud between Comptroller Arthur Levitt and NAR administration; copies of legislation on New York State School Financing Authority.
  - Fiscal - Sales Tax, 1966 (Box 16, Folder 166)
    Correspondence on analysis of impact of state sales tax on various industries; analysis of appeals for exemption from sales tax from various groups and industries; analysis of proposed amendments to sales tax law.
  - Fiscal - Sales Tax - Draft Sales Tax Legislation, 1965 (Box 17, Folder 167)
    Memos on draft sales tax bills.
  - Fiscal - Sales Tax - Draft Sales Tax Legislation, 1965 (Box 17, Folder 168)
    Prints of draft bill.
  - Fiscal - Sales Tax - Draft Sales Tax Legislation, 1965 (Box 17, Folder 169)
    Technical changes and Amendments.
  - Fiscal - Sales Tax Conferences, January-March 1965 (Box 17, Folder 170)
    Correspondence and draft legislation on meetings with representatives of various industries and groups petitioning for exemption from sales tax; analysis of their cases.
  - Fiscal - Sales Tax Conferences, April-October 1965 (Box 17, Folder 171)
  - Fiscal - State Fiscal Picture, 1971 (Box 18, Folder 172)
    Proposed plan for "State-Local Fiscal Relations" to coordinate cost and financing of government programs; 2 drafts of NAR's special message to the Legislature on the state fiscal crisis, April 20, 1971.
  - Fiscal - Tax Law, 1970 (Box 18, Folder 173)
    Printed version of an act to codify New York State Tax Law and an analysis of the act by Acting Commissioner of Taxation and Finance Norman F. Gallman.
  - General Services - Binghamton State Office Building, 1967 (Box 18, Folder 174)
    Correspondence on agreement between New York State, Broome County and Binghamton over construction and use of proposed office building and need for special legislation to construct it and related underground parking garage.
  - General Services - Harlem State Office Building, 1966, 1971-1972 (Box 18, Folder 175)
    Correspondence between Robert R. Douglass, Urban Development Corporation president Ed Logue and NAR on best use of New York State office site in Harlem (New York City), and method of selecting art for the finished building.
  - General Services - Manhattan, 80 Centre Street, 1971-1972 (Box 18, Folder 176)
    Correspondence on proposed transfer of office building from New York State to New York City for court purposes after New York State offices move to World Trade Center. No conclusion here.
  - General Services - South Mall, 1969, 1971-1972 (Box 18, Folder 177)
    Correspondence on development and use.
  - Government - Appalachia, 1965, 1971 (Box 18, Folder 178)
    Two memos; on possibility of New York participating in federal development programs for Appalachia, 1965; on status of Appalachian child development projects, 1971.
  - Government - Big City Problems, 1965 (Box 18, Folder 179)
    NAR's staff analysis of "white papers" issued by New York City Mayor-elect John V. Lindsay. Topics include: The City's Fiscal Problems; Housing and Urban Renewal; Financing Education; Education in the City's Schools; Improving the Economy of New York City; Crime and Safety; Parks and Recreational Facilities; Anti-Poverty; Mass Transportation; New York City Hospitals and Improvement in Health Care; Drug Addiction; Public Welfare. Only a few of the "white papers" are here.
  - Government - Binghamton Welfare, 1971-1972 (Box 19, Folder 180)
    Correspondence, handwritten notes, clippings on Binghamton's fiscal crisis and its inability to make local welfare payments; proposed legislation to merge Broome County's social service agencies to reduce administrative costs.
  - Government - Bureau of Urban Affairs, 1966 (Box 19, Folder 181)
    Three items on establishing an urban affairs division in the Office for Local Development.
  - Government - Census-1970, 1971 (Box 19, Folder 182)
    Preliminary report of 1970 census of New York; U.S. Census Bureau report on migration.
  - Government - County Executives Meeting, 1971 (Box 19, Folder 183)
    Correspondence and press releases on meeting of NAR, Senate and Assembly leaders, and executives of 11 large counties on state's fiscal crisis. Includes background material on sales tax revenues, state aid, revenue sharing, and state mandates.
  - Government - Federal-State Fiscal Relations, 1970 (Box 19, Folder 184)
    A background file of data and statistics on federal revenue sharing.
  - Government - Federal-State Relations, Special Committee, 1965-1966 (Box 19, Folder 185)
    Report of the Cabinet Committee on Federal-State Relations (New York State), MArch 3, 1966; Counsel's Office memo on proposal that local governments must secure state approval before participating in cooperative projects with the federal government or accepting federal financial assistance; press release on appointment of special cabinet committee.
  - Government - Great Lakes Compact, 1966 (Box 19, Folder 186)
    Correspondence on Power Authority of the State of New York;s opposition to the proposed federal legislation requiring dealings with Canada in allocating use of Great Lakes water for power uses be done through the US Department of State.
  - Government - Gualtieri Case, 1967 (Box 19, Folder 187)
    Complaint against NAR by John H. Mulroy, County Executive of Onondaga County, over who has authority to appoint county officers to fill vacancies. Both Mulroy and NAR had appointed Frank A. Gualtieri, Jr., as District Attorney of Onondaga County.
  - Government - Interstate Regional Planning (1967 Program), 1966-1967 (Box 19, Folder 188)
    Two memos proposing Interstate Regional Planning Commission with members from New York, New Jersey, Connecticut and the federal government to review federal aid applications and carry out comprehensive planning.
  - Government - Local Government, 1964 (Box 19, Folder 189)
    Miscellaneous items including 25-page fact sheet on state financial and other assistance to local government; memos and press releases concerning the increasing cost of local government and increasing its efficiency including assessment improvement, use of data processing equipment, federal aid to local government, recodification of zoning laws.
  - Government - Local Government Representatives Meeting, 1964-1966 (Box 19, Folder 190)
    Reviews of miscellaneous legislation concerning local government.
  - Government - Municipal Police Training Council, 1965 (Box 19, Folder 191)